<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A physico medical essay concerning alkaly and acid so far as they have relation to the cause or cure of distempers : wherein is endeavoured to be proved that acids are not (as is generally and erroneously supposed) the cause of all or most distempers, but that alkalies are : together with an account of some distempers and the medicines with their preparations proper to be used in the cure of them : as also a short digression concerning specifick remedies / by John Colbatch.</title>
            <author>Colbatch, John, Sir, 1670-1729.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33709</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26032</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09318111</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09318111</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42743</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33709)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42743)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1305:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A physico medical essay concerning alkaly and acid so far as they have relation to the cause or cure of distempers : wherein is endeavoured to be proved that acids are not (as is generally and erroneously supposed) the cause of all or most distempers, but that alkalies are : together with an account of some distempers and the medicines with their preparations proper to be used in the cure of them : as also a short digression concerning specifick remedies / by John Colbatch.</title>
                  <author>Colbatch, John, Sir, 1670-1729.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[27], 147, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dan. Browne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Formulae, receipts, prescriptions.</term>
               <term>Diseases --  Causes and theories of causation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42743:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42743:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Phyſico Medical ESSAY, CONCERNING ALKALY and ACID, SO FAR As they have relation to the Cauſe or Cure of DISTEMPERS; WHEREIN Is endeavoured to be proved, that Acids are not (as is generally, and erroneouſly ſuppoſed) the Cauſe of all or moſt Diſtempers; but that Alkalies are.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER With an Account of ſome Diſtempers, and the Medicines, with their Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, proper to be uſed in the Cure of them: AS ALSO A Short Digreſſion, concerning Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifick Remedies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By JOHN COLBATCH</hi> Phyſician.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Dan. Browne</hi> at the <hi>Black Swan</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:42743:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42743:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable Sir HENRY BELLASIS, Lieutenant-General OF His Majeſty's Forces.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DEdications are at this time grown ſo much in Faſhion, that a Book which appears in the World without one, is ſcarce look'd upon by any body; people thinking that the Author, who
<pb facs="tcp:42743:3"/> omits a thing ſo generally practiſed, is altogether deſtitute of a Friend who is capable of protecting and countenancing him; and for that very reaſon only, let the merit of the Book be never ſo great, few people will give themſelves the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Reading any more than the Title Page alone. To prevent which, and at the ſame time to manifeſt my Gratitude for the manifold Favours you have been pleas'd Generouſly to heap upon me, I have preſumed to prefix your Name to the following Eſſay. I cannot flatter my ſelf ſo far as to think there is any thing in it worthy to entertain a Perſon of Your
<pb facs="tcp:42743:3"/> Parts: But ſince it comes from one who is filled with a ſenſe of Gratitude, I have ſome reaſon to hope, that it may meet with a kind Acceptance; I very well knowing, that ſmall things have ſometimes a Value ſet upon them, eſpecially when they are made the Offerings of Reſpect, Eſteem, and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. It would be too great an Honour to me, to tell the World with what readineſs you have appeared to Serve me at thoſe times when I have ſtood moſt in need of your Aſſiſtance: For which I cannot better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs my Gratitude, than by a ſilence full of Admiration: For let me ſay never ſo much,
<pb facs="tcp:42743:4"/> I ſhould ſtill fall ſhort of my Duty. This Piece is properly Yours, it being under Your Umbrage that I have been enabled to Write it. And if, out of Your wonted Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, You ſhall be pleaſed to caſt a favourable Aſpect upon it, it will afford the greateſt ſatisfaction to him, who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Great Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Obliged, and moſt Obedient Servant, JO. COLBATCH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:42743:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT may be much wondred at, that I ſhould in the leaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to meddle with this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that hath already been handled by ſo many very Great men. But when it ſhall be well conſidered, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow much different a manner I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eated upon it, from what hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een hitherto done, I queſtion not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut by the generality of Mankind, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be very eaſily excuſed. And
<pb facs="tcp:42743:5"/> though there may be many imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons met with: Yet when the deſign of the thing (it being to undeceive peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in a Matter, upon which depends the Health and Welfare of all) ſhall be well lookt into; I doubt not, but by the candidly ingenious, my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking will be well approved off: Though I expect to meet with a great number of Carpers, eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe, who by long cuſtom, and for want of due conſideration, have embraced a contrary opinion to that of mine.</p>
            <p>It is ſcarce poſſible for a man to converſe with a Perſon that is ill, let the Diſtemper be what it will, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially thoſe, who have any ſmat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering in Phyſick, which moſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple now a days have, but they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb facs="tcp:42743:5"/> tell you, that their blood is ſo very acid, that unleſs that acidity can be corrected, it is impoſſible for them to be well: And accordingly they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently flye to the uſe of Alkalious Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, as Powder of <hi>Pearle, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Crabs eyes,</hi> or ſomething of the ſame nature, and if they ſend for a Phyſician, which few people do, till they have firſt uſed a vaſt Farrago of Alkalious Medicines; and if the Phyſician chances to take the ſame method, that they themſelves had before done, they preſently cry out, we have already taken ſuch vaſt quantities of the beforementioned Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, that unleſs you can think of ſome more generous and efficacious Alkalies, the Acids complained off, are not to be mortified: Which has
<pb facs="tcp:42743:6"/> put men to great ſhifts either to find out new, or to diſguiſe the old ones: yet after all, the Patients expectation has been fruſtrated, their Diſtempers not being to be cured, by Medicines of that Nature, but on the contrary either to be exaſperated, or ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, that they will ſcarce ever ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a cure at all, eſpecially if the Diſtemper be a Chronick one.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, that I my ſelf have formerly been a ſtickler for Alkalies, (being carried away by the common vogue of Mankind) and ſeeing the inſufficiency of common Alkalies, have put my ſelf to great expence, beſides a vaſt deal of trouble, to Volatilize Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> &amp;c. till at laſt I was fully ſatisfied, by daily obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, that Alkalies, though never
<pb facs="tcp:42743:6"/> ſo exalted, would do me very little, if any ſervice at all in the cure of moſt Diſtempers.</p>
            <p>There are ſome particular prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Steel and Antimony, ſome of which I have given an account off, the which giving as Alkalies, and as they are generally believed to be, did me very great ſervice. But ſince I have well examined them, inſtead of Alkalies, I find them to be moſt noble Acids, and the Diſtempers cured by them, did not (as I formerly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) proceed, from any abundance of acid Particles in the Blood or Juices. But on the contrary from Alkalious ones, as I ſuppoſe, moſt Diſtempers do, and as I have endeavoured to make appear by many Obſervations.</p>
            <p>I expect a great many will cry out
<pb facs="tcp:42743:7"/> as ſome have already done, that this Man was bred an Apothecary, and ſhall he pretend to be a reformer in Phyſick and Surgery.</p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that their Charge I own, confeſſing my ſelf to have been an Apothecary, and was bred up under a man (though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a very honeſt and juſt Perſon) that was not the greateſt Maſter in his buſineſs. I taking notice of my Maſters imperfections, applied my ſelf, for four years of the time I lived with him, to diligent Study, in order to become Maſter of thoſe things, I was ſenſible my Maſter could not teach me, And after I had well conſidered, and in ſome meaſure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Maſter in Pharmarcy, which is the Foundation, upon which the
<pb facs="tcp:42743:7"/> Practice of Phyſick is built: I was at laſt induced to look into the Body of Phyſick it ſelf, and though I don't pretend to abſolute maſterſhip, yet I ſhall endeavour, and think my ſelf oblidged in Duty, both to God and Man, to improve my ſmall Talent to the beſt advantage I can, let Carpers ſay what they will.</p>
            <p>The greateſt part of my time, I lived in <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and although I kept an Apothecaries-Shop, yet my Dependance was wholly upon my own Practice, the ſucceſs I had in which, is ſufficiently known in that Country. And for a Character, I deſire no other or better, then the generality of thoſe People will give me, of whom I know not one, that can or will ſpeak amiſs of me, for any thing, but my
<pb facs="tcp:42743:8"/> coming away from them, and leaving ſuch flouriſhing, thriving buſineſs, that ſcarce any man of my Age ever had before me. For which many of them have blamed me. But the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of my leaving that place, are best known to my ſelf.</p>
            <p>And ſince I have been ſpeaking concerning my own being bred an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary, I ſhall enlarge a little upon that ſubject, giving a ſhort account of the neceſſary qualifications of one of that Profeſſion, and then ſhall leave every body to judge, whether a man ſo qualified has not made a large ſtep, towards being a good Phyſician.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> An Apothecary muſt be very well acquainted with the Vegitable Kingdom, not only to know the faces of Plants, but their Natures and
<pb facs="tcp:42743:8"/> manner of Operation upon Humane Bodies, otherwiſe, how can he tell how to handle them, ſo as to make his Compoſitions as they ought to be. And indeed every Phyſician ſuppoſes the Apothecary ſo qualified when he Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes to his Shop; for in his Bill, he ſeldom directs the method of making his Medicines, but only orders ſuch and ſuch Medicines, knowing or at laſt ſuppoſing them (for every Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician ought to be well ſatisfied in the Abilities of an Apothecary, before he preſcribes to him) to be before hand skilfully prepared. For let a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician Preſcribe like an Angel, if the Apothecary through his ignorance in his buſineſs, be deſtitute of good and well prepared Medicines, both Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician and Patient are fruſtrated in
<pb facs="tcp:42743:9"/> their expectations, the which I am affraid to frequently happens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He muſt well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Nature and Operation of Minerals and Mettals, which is not to be learnt in the Diſpenſitary, nor any other way to be attained, but by much reading and hard labour in the fire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He muſt underſtand the Nature of Animal Bodies alſo, amongſt which is comprehended that of Man, there being ſcarce a part of whole Body, but what is ſometime or other to be uſed as Medicine: But before it is uſed, the Apothecaries skill is for the moſt part required for its preparation, in order to which, he ought firſt of all, very well to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand its Nature.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42743:9"/>
            <p>All the forementioned qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and a great many more, are mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Apothecaries in <hi>England</hi> endowed with: And to the Honour of the Apothecaries of <hi>London,</hi> be it ſpoken, I have generally found the meaneſt Shops in that Eminent City, better fraited with good Medicines, then any of the moſt Eminent in all <hi>Holland,</hi> or the reſt of the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might add a great deal more on the behalf of that noble Profeſſion, which although, I my ſelf have left it off, yet ſtill have a high value and eſteem for it, and think an honeſt and skilfull Apothecary, is as ſerviceable in the Common-wealth, and deſerves as much incouragement, and is as highly to be valued, as any man what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42743:10"/>
            <p>The Famous <hi>Ettmuler,</hi> was not aſhamed to own, that he ſerved eight years to an Apothecary. Yet for all that, he afterwards became one of the eminenteſt Phyſicians of <hi>Europe.</hi> And for ought I know, the loſs of him at the Age he died, from whom ſo much might rationally have been expected, deſerves as much to be lamented, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by Phyſicians, as the loſs of any one private man.</p>
            <p>I have not given a full account of thoſe Diſtempers I have treated on, but given ſome ſhort hints concerning them, ſo far as was neceſſary to clear my way as I went.</p>
            <p>I have in the following Eſſay, made reflections upon the Practice of ſome particular men only, my deſign not being in the leaſt, to reflect upon
<pb facs="tcp:42743:10"/> that Noble Society, or Body of Men, or any Member of them, I mean the Colledge of Phyſicians, whom I own to be the Glory of our Nation, and of the whole World, and for whom I have the greateſt reverence and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect imaginable.</p>
            <p>I don't pretend to be the ſole Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or firſt broacher of this Doctrine of Acids, in the cure of Diſtempers, it having long ſince been the opinion, of ſome of the moſt happy Practiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners in the World, and is at this time embraced, by ſeveral of the greateſt men, that perhaps our age affords.</p>
            <p>I wrote this Eſſay at a place, (during the firſt three Weeks of the Siege of the Caſtle of <hi>Namur,</hi> in which time, we had not many wounded men, brought to our Field-Hoſpital) where I had
<pb facs="tcp:42743:11"/> not the oppertunity of conſulting Books, nor had I the benefit of coming at my one Papers, wherein I had from time to time ſet down my Obſervations upon this Subject: For want of which I have only made uſe of thoſe that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred to my memory, which is a very treacherous one, and ſo they are not ſo numerous nor exact as I deſigned them: But however for ſome reaſons I am willing to venture them abroad as they are, they not being in the leaſt deſigned to entertain the Learned, but to undeceive the Multitude.</p>
            <p>I don't pretend to be ſo great a man, nor to deſerve ſo well of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind as <hi>Helmont, Paracelſus,</hi> &amp;c. have done, yet they treading out of the common Paths, and acting upon dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Principles, from the reſt of
<pb facs="tcp:42743:11"/> Mankind: They did not want thoſe, who maligned and hated them, and uſed all the opprobrious Language in the World againſt them. Therefore why ſhould I, who don't in the leaſt pretend to have arrived to thoſe great Perfections, that they had attained to, take it amiſs to be abuſed and evil ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>Authority has in great meaſure, blinded ſome mens underſtandings, and ſealed up their eyes. There being ſtill a ſort of men, that pay too ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive a deference to ancient Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, tho' never ſo contrary to reaſon, that they will not open their eyes to ſee or underſtand the truth. There are ſtill men who write againſt moſt known Truths, as againſt the gravity and Elaſtick force of the Air, and
<pb facs="tcp:42743:12"/> other things of the ſame Nature. This Doctrine of Acids, and that I former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrote concerning the Cure of Wounds, are likewiſe of the number of thoſe that are unfortunate, meerly for want of being born old and with a venerable Beard.</p>
            <p>When a Book (ſays the Famous <hi>Malbranch)</hi> is firſt to appear in the World, one knows not whom to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult to know its deſtiny. The Stars preſide not over its Nativity: Their influences have no operation on it; and the moſt confident Aſtrologers dare not foretel, the divers riſques of fortune it muſt run. Truth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this World, Caeleſtial Bodies have no power over her; and whereas ſhe is of a moſt ſpiritual Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the ſeveral poſitions or combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:42743:12"/> of Matter, can contribute no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, either to her eſtabliſhment or ruin. Beſides the judgments of men are ſo different in reſpect of the ſame things, that we can never more hazardouſly and imprudently play the Prophet, then in preſaging the happy or unfortunate ſucceſs of a Book. So that every man who ventures to be an Author, at the ſame time throws himſelf, at the Readers mercy, to make him, or eſteem him, what he pleaſes. But of all Authors, thoſe who encounter with prejudices, ought moſt infallibly to reckon upon their condemnation. Their Works ſit too uneaſie upon moſt mens minds, and if they eſcape the paſſions of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies (which I have not done) they are obliged to the Almighty
<pb facs="tcp:42743:13"/> force of Truth for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
            <p>However time will do every man Juſtice, and Truth, which at firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a Chymerical and ridiculous Phantaſm, by degrees, grows ſenſible and manifeſt. Men open their eyes and contemplate her, they diſcover her charms and fall in love with her.</p>
            <p>The Books that encounter with prejudices, leading to Truths through unbeaten Paths, require much longer time than others, to obtain the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion their Authors expect them. And I find it but too true in my ſelf, that all thoſe Writers who combate with prejudices, are much miſtaken if they think by that means, to recommend themſelves to the favour and eſteem of others. Poſſibly ſome few, will ſpeak
<pb facs="tcp:42743:13"/> honourably of them when they are dead. But whilſt they live, they muſt expect to be neglected (I ſpeak experimentally) by moſt people, and to be deſpiſed, reviled, and perſecuted, even by thoſe, who go for the wiſeſt and moſt moderate ſort of men.</p>
            <p>There is nothing but Truth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in my <hi>Novum Lumen Chyrurgicum,</hi> and I did think that I ſhould have been put into a condition this Summer, to have made it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appear. But instead of that, I have been abuſed and delivered up into the hands of my enemies, to do with me as they pleaſed.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Novum Lumen</hi> is built upon a pair of Medicines, the which as yet I think not fit to make publick, but here lyes my misfortune, common
<pb facs="tcp:42743:14"/> to all thoſe, who make new Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. A great many believe the Truth of what I have ſaid, and that my Medicines are capable of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming what I have promiſed for them. But amongſt the number of thoſe, who are ſo ingenuous as to believe matter of fact, a great many ſay, this man was not the Author, others that they have the ſame Medicines, and ſome that they imparted them to me. As for theſe Gentlemen, I can very eaſily excuſe them, I very well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it is the Nature of moſt Men, not to allow any Perſon the honour of his own Diſcoveries, they thinking that thereby, their own Glory is eclipſed. But there are another ſort of Men, whoſe Intereſt, will not give them leave to embrace
<pb facs="tcp:42743:14"/> the Truth, and for the ſame reaſon they do what in them lies, to keep others from ſo doing. And the greateſt part of Mankind not being judges in my cauſe, any further then their eyes direct them, and it being altogether impoſſible, that there ſhould be any great number of Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, by which means I am evil ſpoken off by many, upon no other grounds, then becauſe an intereſted party have told them, that I have pretended to what I can't perform.</p>
            <p>I expect the mouths of my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies will be opened very wide againſt me, but I have already born ſo much, that I can with a great deal of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedneſs bear with the greateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities that can be offered me: My great ſatisfaction being, that I have
<pb facs="tcp:42743:15"/> peace in my own breaſt, having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed nothing but what tended to the good of Mankind: And very well knowing, that if my Medicines are faithfully and skilfully uſed, they are capable of performing much more then I have promiſed for them; but the beſt Medicines unskilfully uſed, or with a deſign that they ſhould not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by prejudiced Perſons, may be brought into diſgrace.</p>
            <p>The following Eſſay I humbly offer to the candid Readers ſerious conſideration, nothing doubting but that it will meet with a favourable reception from ſome few. And I muſt needs ſay, that I more value the good Opinion and good Word of one candidly ingenuous, then all that can be ſaid againſt me, by ten thouſand
<pb facs="tcp:42743:15"/> clamarous ill-natured Perſons. I have endeavoured to act and behave my ſelf ſo, as to deſerve no mans ill Word; but if I am abuſed and my Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings miſrepreſented without any juſt cauſe, I ſhall never break my heart about it, I very well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the juſtice and integrity of my Undertakings, will one time or other be made appear.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Houſe in St. <hi>Anns</hi> Court, in <hi>Dean-Street,</hi> near <hi>Soho-Square,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>October</hi> the <hi>12th.</hi> 1695.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb facs="tcp:42743:16"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42743:16"/>
            <head>A Phyſico Medical ESSAY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Small Pox.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE firſt thing I ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with, is the diſuſe of Alkalies in the Small-Pox, that fatal Diſtemper to three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and even all <hi>Europe:</hi> In that, by the means of it, God was pleaſed to deprive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, whoſe worth was ſuch, that a value ſufficient can never be ſet upon it, and whoſe loſs ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently be lamented.</p>
               <p>It is a common pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce, both
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42743:17"/> of Nurſes and the generality of Practitioners, as ſoon as they perceive the leaſt Symptoms of this Diſtemper, to give either <hi>Gaſcons,</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Kents, Lapis de Goa,</hi> or ſome other Teſtaceous Powder, which are known Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalies. The one Party as they pretend to drive the Malignity from the Heart; the other to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the Acidity which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture (for beyond conjecture they can't go) to be in the <hi>blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſubſequent Diſcourſe, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew, upon what falſe ſuppoſitions both Parties go.</p>
               <p>For the firſt ſort, it will not be worth while to ſpend much time about them, by reaſon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one will readily grant,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42743:17"/> that they generally act upon wrong and miſtaken Notions. For, for any Malignity to be lodged in the Heart, more than any other part, is altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, by reaſon that the Blood moves ten times at leaſt faſter through the Heart than any other part, the Lungs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted: For the Cavities being large, no Stagnation is to be feared, and ſo by conſequence no danger. If there be any danger of the Malignities ſetling any where, it muſt be in thoſe parts where the Veſſels are very ſmall, and the Blood moves but ſlowly, which muſt be near the extream Parts.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond ſort, who give
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42743:18"/> the ſame Medicines, but with quite different Intentions; I ſhall endeavour to prove, that their ſuppoſitions are altogether as falſe and groundleſs as the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. They give their Alkalious Medicines, to correct the Aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity they ſuppoſe to be in the Blood, and which is, as they pretend, the occaſion of all the ill Symptoms that attend People in the Small-Pox: Now I could never hear of any one, that by Analyzing the Blood of Perſons in the Small-Pox, that could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver find the leaſt footſteps of Acidity in it; though on the contrary it doth appear, after many trials, that the Blood of ſuch Perſons, doth more abound
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42743:18"/> with Alkalious Particles, then that of ſound People: So by conſequence, the giving of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalies in this caſe muſt be at leaſt ſuperfluous, if not highly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious, and as I have frequently obſerved, and ſhall inſtance in ſome particulars.</p>
               <p>The cauſe of the Small-Pox, common with moſt other Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors and acute Diſtempers, I ſuppoſe to be, from a quantity of ſuch Particles, being ſome way or other admitted into the Blood, which being of a quite different Texture from that of the Blood, and ſo not capable of being mixt with it, cauſes a hurry and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der there, which is what I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42743:19"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Nov. Lum. Chyr.</note> elſewhere obſerve, to be the occaſion of both continued and Sympto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Fevers. Now it is well known, that a Fever always precedes the Eruption of the Puſtles in the Small-Pox: And when the Puſtles are well come out, that is, when the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogeneous or Particles of a different Texture from thoſe of the Blood, are thrown out to the Surface of the Body, then the Fever ceaſes.</p>
               <p>Now to aſſiſt Nature in throwing thoſe Heterogeneous Particles out of the Blood, to the extream Parts, which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be mightily hindred, by a great quantity of Acids in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42743:19"/> Blood, they give repeated, and large quanties of Teſtatious, Alkalious Powders, and other Diaphoreticks: Which indeed ſeldom fail of anſwering their Intentions, in throwing out large quantities of Puſtles, even more than Nature is able to ſupply or bring to maturity; and if ſhe doth chance to cope with them, is the only occaſion of ſpoyling ſo many angelick Faces, as we every day obſerve. But the ſpoyling of Faces is not all, for beſides the throwing out of ſo great a quantity of Puſtles, by breaking off the Globules of the Blood, when it is brought to the Cataneous Glands, inſtead of thoſe Glands ſeparating the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crementitious
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42743:20"/> Serum, which in a State of Health, is all or moſt part of it, to be carried off by ſweat or inſenſible tranſpiration, but at this time to ſupply the Puſtles till they are brought to maturity. I ſay by breaking off the Globules of the Blood, when it is in its confuſed State, Serum and all together; the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crementitious Serum only, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rules of Nature, ought to be ſeparated, thoſe Glands being ſo many ſtrainers, adapted to receive into them the Serum only, and not the leaſt drop of Blood, when it is in its natural State, and its Globules un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broken. I can liken the ſeparation of the Serum from the Blood, by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42743:20"/> the mediation of the cutaneous Glands, to nothing better, then to a mixture of <hi>oyl</hi> and <hi>water,</hi> made by continued agitation, when that compound mixture ſeems to be one intire white liquor, tho' with good eyes or a good glaſs, the <hi>oyl</hi> may be ſeen floating in the Water in ſmall Globules, as the Blood doth in the Serum, as I elſewhere <note n="*" place="margin">Nov. Lum. Chyr.</note> obſerve: Yet this mixture of Oyl and Water, let it be done never ſo exactly, if it be poured into a funnil, lined with brown Paper, wet before hand, the Pores will be ſo diſpoſed, as to let all the Water run through, though not the leaſt Particle of the Oyl; yet if there be ſome
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42743:21"/> Alkalious Salts, boyled with this mixture of Oyl and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Globules of the Oyl will be ſo broken, as to paſs readily with the Water, through the forementioned brown Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which before it would not in the leaſt do. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Globules of the Blood being broken, by the means of Alkalious Medicines, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with too great a quantity of Alkalious Particles, being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore admitted into it, is by that means made capable of being received into the Cutaneous Glands, which is the only oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of thoſe purple ſpots upon the ſurface of the skin, not only in the Small-Pox, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42743:21"/> other Fevers, which ſpots ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or never fail of being the certain Prognoſticators of future Death.</p>
               <p>But this is not all, for by the foreſaid breaking of the Globules of the Blood, by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalious Medicines, theſe ſmall broken Globules, getting into the ſmall Meanders of the Brain, hinder the Motion of the Animal Spirits, through the Nerves, and ſo cauſe Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riums, and all thoſe fatal diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders of the Brain, that are but too frequently ſeen.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe the Blood not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing capable of being contained in its proper Channels, is the occaſion of violent Bleeding at
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42743:22"/> the Noſe, bloody Urine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are none of the beſt Symptoms, but what too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently happen by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid means.</p>
               <p>Beſides breaking of the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bules of the Blood, and cauſing the ill Symptoms before-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, with many others, I don't think fit here to enumerate: By their Diaphoretick quality, there is ſo vaſt a waſte made of the Serum of the <hi>blood,</hi> that there is not a ſufficient quantity left, to ſupply and bring to maturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, thoſe many Puſtles, (even more than Nature deſigned) that thoſe Medicines alone had thrown out: So that about the ninth, eleventh, or thirteenth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42743:22"/> day, for want of a ſufficient quantity of Serum to ſupply them, the Puſtles fall, and the Acrid corroſive matter, being abſorbed into the Blood, cauſes ſecondary Fevers, which often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times prove of very dangerous conſequence. I might expati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate a great deal more, but I deſign brevity.</p>
               <p>It may be ſaid, you have gone far enough in condemning the ordinary Practice, as to the uſe of Alkalies and Diaphoreticks, not having ſubſtituted a better and ſafer Method and Medicines in their room: but not too faſt, that follows in its proper place.</p>
               <p>The Small-Pox, is a Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, that requires the giving of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42743:23"/> as few Medicines, as in any Diſtemper whatſoever, unleſs in ſome extraordinary caſes: But yet I think it the moſt unreaſonable thing in the World, that People (as is the common practice in this caſe) ſhould be left to the ſole ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of old Women and Nurſes; which thing alone, I verily believe, has been the deſtruction of more people, than the Sword it ſelf. And although but very few Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, as I ſaid before, are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally neceſſary, yet the eye of a careful, skilful Phyſitian, and that from the beginning, is as convenient as in any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper whatſoever, that he
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42743:23"/> ſeeing Natures operations, may alſo ſee the fit time, when to give the Medicines requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite. I confeſs I have heard ſome people complain, that ſuch a Phyſitian has had ſo many Fees, and never wrote one Bill for them; for ſuch people, let me tell them, that they complain without cauſe, for in many caſes, eſpecially in this, the Phyſitian deſerves his Fees better for not writing at all, then for ſo doing.</p>
               <p>I own my ſelf to be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Chymiſt, and in many things, though not all, a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of <hi>Helmont,</hi> and know nothing in this World, ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful to me, as Chymical
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42743:24"/> Operations: Yet in this caſe, nor indeed in ſcarce any acute Diſtemper, do I judge Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Medicines to be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary, though many of them may do well, and are ſometimes to be uſed: But I don't know any reaſon we have to flye to elaborate Preparations, when Nature has provided Medicines ready to our hands. Acids are the things skilfully and timely gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which I have ſeen, not only by my own, but by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Great mens Practice, to be the only ſafe, effectual, and ſeldom or never erring Medicines in this Diſtemper, ſo that they are rightly timed,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42743:24"/> and given with diſcretion; and why ſhould we flye to Acids Chymically prepared, when as I ſaid before, Nature has provided to our hands, Oranges, Lemmons, Cittrons, Limes, and a great many more, not neceſſary here to mention, which for the moſt part anſwer our Intentions, ſo that they are skilfully gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by an experienced hand. And as, I hope, I have given ſufficient reaſons to diſſwade the uſe of Alkalies and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoreticks, from the many direful effects that daily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend their uſe, ſo I hope to give as cogent ones to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the uſe of Acids, from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42743:25"/> the laudable, good effects, I have ſeen from them; for in five hundred (at leaſt) Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, that I have had of all Qualities to do with, in this Diſtemper, in <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> where I have been called in at the beginning of the Diſtemper, I do not know that I have had one that has died or been disfigured; nay, ſome that have been brought into very ill circumſtances, by the precedent uſe of Teſtaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Alkalious Powders and Diaphoreticks, I have retriev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the jaws of impen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding death, by the uſe of fit and proper Acids.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:42743:25"/>
               <p>It may be wondred at by ſome, that I make a difference between Teſtacious Powders and Diaphoreticks, when the Teſtatious Powders, eſpecially the compound ones, as <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> Powder, Counteſs of <hi>Kents, Lapis de Goa,</hi> &amp;c. are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Diaphoreticks, and indeed are ſo: But the reaſon why I do it, is, becauſe for the moſt part beſides the ſaid Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalious Powders, other more forcible Diaphoreticks are alſo given.</p>
               <p>I having in ſhort given ſome hints concerning the cauſe of the Small-Pox, I need not again repeat them, ſo I ſhall immediately proceed to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42743:26"/> the method I take in the cure of it, which being according to Natures dictates, is ſhort and eaſie: For Nature in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming her Operations, makes ſhort and eaſie cuts, it being in the cure of Diſeaſes, as in finding out and giving an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> of Nature by Phyloſophical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions; they that go upon the feweſt Principles, general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover moſt of her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, and are capable of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the beſt and moſt rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal account of them: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they that are clogged with multiplicity of Principles, and wandring in tedious, long, and uncouth Paths, thinking there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42743:26"/> to get admiſſion into Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Cabinet, after they have ſpent much time, and taken a great deal of pains, at laſt fit down as wiſe as when they began, and not one jot the wiſer.</p>
               <p>Firſt of all, when I come to a Patient who has the Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms of the Small-Pox upon them, which are ſo well known, even to Nurſes, that I need not ſpend any time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them. In the firſt place, if there be any manifeſt ſigns of the Stomachs being op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and clogged with viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous Matter, as generally it is, I firſt of all give a gentle, eaſie vomit, ſuitable to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42743:27"/> age and conſtitution of the Patients, and after that hath done operating ſome <hi>Syrupus E Meconio,</hi> or any other pro-Opiat in due proportion. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, to allay the hurry and diſorder in the Blood, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by the intromiſſion of Hetrogeneous Particles, which Nature is endeavouring to throw out: And to confirm the Texture of the Blood, ſo as to enable it to rid it ſelf of its enemy, I give large quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of any of the following Julips.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take of freſh juice of civil Oranges ſix Ounces, Barly Water one quart, double refined Sugar</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:42743:27"/> 
                  <hi>as much as is ſufficient to make it grateful, or to thoſe Palats or Stomachs (which are very few) to whom juice of Oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges is ungrateful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take of juice of Lemmons, or Lime juice that is not muſty, four Ounces, Barly Water one quart, Cinnamon Water half an Ounce, Syrup of Rasberries as much as is ſufficient to make it grateful: Or,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take of Barly, Cinnamon Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one quart, juice of Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons four Ounces, Syrup of Wood-Sorrel three Ounces, mix and make a Julip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O any of theſe Julips, I give my Patients to drink
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42743:28"/> as oft and as freely as they pleaſe: Drinking likewiſe ſmall Beer with juice of Oranges in it, in as large quantities as they pleaſe. But during the whole courſe of the Diſtemper, all ſorts of fleſh ought to be avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p>To poor people, inſtead of the aforeſaid Julips, and to ſave charges, I order them large quantities of ſmall Beer, acidulated with Oyl of Vitriol, or inſtead of that Vinegar or Verjuice Poſſet drink, to be drank frequently, and in large quantities.</p>
               <p>But if in the beginning
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42743:28"/> or at any other time, I find the Brain very much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed, and the Patient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lirious, I for the moſt part find it abſolutely neceſſary to let Blood, and that in a good quantity; and then to flye to the uſe of more powerful Acids, giving the following Julips in large quantities, which preſently calms the violent Motion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Agitation of the Blood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Spirit, and ſets <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll to rights in a ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take of Barly, Cinamon-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r one quart, Syrup of Ras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>erries three Ounces, Volatile</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:42743:29"/> 
                  <hi>Spirit of Vitriol one Dram and half, or mix and make a Julip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take of Barly, Cinnamon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water one quart, Syrup of Ras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries three Ounces, Gas Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phuris as much as is ſufficient to make it ſharp: Or,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take of Barly Water one quart, Epidemick Water two Ounces, Syrup of Wood Sorrel three Ounces, ſweet Spirit of Niter or Vitriol two Scruples: Or,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take of red Roſe Leaves ſix Drams, put them into an earthen or glaſs Veſſel, pour upon them one quart of boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Water, let them ſtand co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered for ſome time, then pour on them two Scruples of Oyl of Vitriol, or Oyl of Sulphur</hi> pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:42743:29"/> Campanam, <hi>when cold, strain out, and add as much double refined Sugar as is ſufficient to make it grateful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If at any time, I find my Patients Spirits languid and low, I then give three or four ſpoonfuls of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Cordial at due in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervals.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take of Aqua Mirabilis, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demick Water, of each three Ounces, Spirit of Citrons half an Ounce, Balm Water eight Ounces, Syrup of Gilliflowers one Ounce and half, mix and make a Julip.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:42743:30"/>
               <p>By this method, I have brought my Patients through the Diſtemper, without ſo much (almoſt) as the leaſt uneaſineſs, or even confining themſelves to their Beds, and without the leaſt fear of a ſecondary Fever, which is that, which frequently proves of moſt fatal conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
               <p>After the Puſtles are quite gone, I then take care to purge them well for five or ſix times, with gentle and eaſie Purges, after each Purge, giving an Hypnot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick: After that I have done Purging, for ſome time I give corroborating,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42743:30"/> ſtrengthning Medicines, to confirm the Texture of the blood and Juices, and bring them to their natural State, by which means I prevent ill accidents, that ſometimes ſucceed the Small-Pox.</p>
               <p>I have not given a full Hiſtory of this Diſtemper, that being contrary to my deſign, but endeavoured to deter people from the uſe of thoſe Methods and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines that have proved fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to ſo many, and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance a better and ſafer Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and Medicines in their room: Yet I would not have people, wholly to rely upon the Method I have here
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:42743:31"/> ſet down, but always have a Phyſitian by, to obviate any unuſual Symptoms, that may chance to appear contrary to what general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do, and where life lies at ſtake, people can't be too cautious. But if the good old Woman and Nurſes, in ſpight of all that can be ſaid, will be ſtill tampering, I muſt needs ſay this, that if my Method were exactly followed by every body from the beginning, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any variation, I verily believe that there would not one in ten die, that have formerly done by the uſe of Alkalies and Diapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:42743:31"/>
               <p>As I have before en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to explode the uſe of Alkalies, and to give my reaſons for ſo doing, ſo I ſhall now endeavour to give ſome reaſons for the Method I take, with the great uſe of Acids in this caſe.</p>
               <p>As I have before obſerved, I judge the cauſe of the Small Pox, to be from an intromiſſion of Heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, or Particles of a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Nature and Texture from the blood into it; by the means of which Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, the blood is put into a very great hurry and diſorder, in order to throw off its
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42743:32"/> enemy, and that the place that Nature deſigns the diſcharge of theſe Particles by, to be the cutaneous Glands. Now the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, that I obſerved to attend the uſe of Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, were the throwing out of more Puſtles than Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deſigned, the deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Globules of the blood, and a waſte of too great a quantity of Serum. I had before forgotten to mention one diſmal effect of Alkalies and Diaphore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and that is by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying or breaking the Globules of the Blood, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of regular Puſtles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:42743:32"/> thrown out to the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Skin, the divided broken Globules are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the morbifick matter thrown out, as in the caſe of—and ſo cauſes an <hi>Eriſpelas</hi> or St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonies</hi> Fire, which ſeldom or never fails of proving fatal.</p>
               <p>Now I almoſt defie any one to ſay that he ever obſerved ſuch Symptoms as theſe, if Acids were from the beginning uſed. For Acids are of that Nature, that they confirm the Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Blood, which is that red ſubſtance, wherein is contained the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:42743:33"/> 
                  <hi>Byolyenium</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Nov. Lum. Chyr.</note> or Lamp of Life; by ſo doing, Nature is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of throwing out the extraneous Particles, in a way ſuitable to it, and without the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies that attend the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther method: For the Texture of the Blood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confirmed, and mov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing regularly and Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in its proper Channels, the morbifick Particles are only thrown out, and ſuch a quantity of Serum left, as is ſufficient to ſupply the Puſtles and bring them to maturity without any danger of their flatuing, and the acrid
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:42743:33"/> Matter; being again ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorbed into the Blood, and cauſing ſecondary Fevers: Beſides the Globules of the Blood being kept toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unbroken, there is not any danger of their being extravaſated, and cauſing thoſe fatal purple Spots. Nor of being thrown out together with morbifick Matter, and ſo cauſing an <hi>Eriſipelas</hi> or St. <hi>Anthonies</hi> Fire; neither are Hemoragies at the the Noſe, bloody Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the leaſt to be feared, nor by being admitted into the ſmall Meanders of the Brain to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:42743:34"/> cauſe Deliriums, and thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Symptoms that attend it.</p>
               <p>I might expatiate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on continued Fevers and ſome other acute Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers: But that would be to be guilty of Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tology: For I aſſign but one general cauſe of them, though I own that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traneous Particles, cauſing them, may be ſomewhat different, and according to the different ſize of the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Particles, the parts affected may be different; as in the Small-Pox, the ſize of the Particles are ſuch, as to fit them to be thrown out by the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneous
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:42743:34"/> Glands to the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Skin; in other Fevers they are thrown out, ſometimes one way, ſometimes another, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ſize. For inſtance, ſometimes they are thrown out by critical ſweating, ſometimes by Urine, ſometimes by the Glands of the Mouth in ſpitting, and ſo on, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the different diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Particles cauſing the Diſtemper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fitted to be diſcharged through the Pores of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Parts: And which ever way we find Nature enclined to do her work,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:42743:35"/> we muſt aſſiſt her in it, but not ſpur her on unleſs ſhe be too ſluggiſh, but muſt not, upon any account whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, hinder or thwart her in her Operations.</p>
               <p>In moſt continued Fevers, I have found Alkalies equally pernicious, as in the Small-Pox; and Acids equally ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious, the which I ſhall inſtance in one or two par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
               <p>After I came out of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> laſt year, being ninety four, having diſcourſed with a certain Phyſitian about a Fever that had that Summer raged in <hi>London,</hi> and of which many died; he told me, that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:42743:35"/> when he found his Patients un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch and ſuch circumſtances, that he as much gave them up for dead, as if a Dagger were run through their Hearts. I asked him what thoſe Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms were, that rendred his Patients circumſtances to be ſo very dangerous? He replied, That when he found them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lirious, and had Spaſmes and Convulſions of the Nerves. I enquired of him, what Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines he gave? He told me, a Compoſition of <hi>Gaſcons</hi> Powder, <hi>Virginian</hi> Snake Root, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which was what he ſolely relied on, and which is the ſame or of the ſame Nature, with what is generally given in thoſe caſes.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:42743:36"/> I asked him whether he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found his Medicine ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to him? He ingeniouſly confeſſed, that when his Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents were under the aforeſaid circumſtances, it never did him any ſervice at all. I again asked him why he did not vary his Method? His reply was, It was a moſt noble Alkaly and Alexipharmick, and what was generally uſed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he did not think fit to vary from an Eſtabliſhed Method.</p>
               <p>A few days after, I was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into a Gentlewoman, exactly under the ſame Circumſtances before related, ſhe being deliri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the higheſt degree, had violent Spaſmes and Convulſions
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:42743:36"/> of the Nerves, and all other Symptoms of a Malignant Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Of her Life I did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, and by the plentiful uſe of proper Acids, all Symptoms ſoon vaniſhed, and in a weeks time, ſhe was fit to go abroad.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, I could inſtance a hundred caſes of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but I deſign brevity.</p>
               <p>I muſt own, that other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers may be complicated with the Small-Pox, and other continued Fevers and acute Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, or from a different con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Air, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unuſual <hi>Symptoms</hi> may appear, in which caſes a general <hi>method</hi> muſt not be relied on, but recourſe muſt be alſo had to proper Specificks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:42743:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Scurvy.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Am now come to treat up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the diſuſe of Alkalies in the Scurvy, that reigning Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper, which few people are altogether free from, and is by moſt men accounted incurable, or at leaſt, it for the moſt part proves ſo.</p>
               <p>But here I expect the cry of all Mankind againſt me; What! ſay there is no Acidity in the Blood in the Scurvy? What! is it but an Acidity in the Blood that is the occaſion of the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:42743:37"/> out of Scabs, Pimples, Blotches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon the Skin? What! but a ſharpneſs and Acidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Blood, occaſions thoſe wandring Pains, and a thouſand other Symptoms, that people labouring under that Diſtemper complain of?</p>
               <p>My Friends, have a little pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and I will preſently make it appear to you, that thoſe Symptoms are not occaſioned by Acids, but from Acrid, Lixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, Alkalious Particles, which I doubt not to evince by plain matter of fact.</p>
               <p>Firſt of all, by a Chymical Analyſis, it doth appear, that the Blood of Scorbutick Perſons, hath by much a greater quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:42743:38"/> of Volatile, Alkalious Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, then that of ſound Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, beſides which ſome quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, more or leſs, of a Lixivious fixt Alkaly, which, for as much as ever I could find, the Blood of ſound Perſons is altogether deſtitute of.</p>
               <p>And by the way give me leave to add this. It is my opinion, that if Phyſitians would give themſelves the trouble of Chymically Analyzing the Blood of Perſons in all Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and making nice Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of the different ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be obtained from it: By that means the cauſe of Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers would be certainly known, and by conſequence the cure of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:42743:38"/> them much more certain, then now it is. But that I may return to my buſineſs.</p>
               <p>Another conſiderable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, beſides that beforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, to prove that the Scurvy hath its riſe from Alkalious ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in the blood, and not from Acids, is this which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
               <p>I have been frequently told, by ſome Seamen and Surgeons, that have been long Voyages at Sea, eſpecially towards <hi>China</hi> and the <hi>Indies,</hi> that of a hundred Men that have been in a Ship, not two of them but have been almoſt eaten up with the Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, their Skin ſquallid and full of blotches, their Gums eaten
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:42743:39"/> away, and their Teeth ready to drop out, Pains and Aches all over their bodies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet upon their landing at <hi>Cadiz</hi> or thereabouts, where are plenty of Oranges and Lemmons, upon eating large quantities of them, in one Fortnights time, at far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt, ſcarce one hath failed of being perfectly cured. This is not a bare relation of one or two Perſons only, but what is generally agreed-upon and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by all people.</p>
               <p>Although theſe moderate Acids plentifully uſed, may have ſuch effects in that hot Country, yet I have not obſerved that in our cold Climate, they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, always I ſay, the ſame <hi>effect,</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:42743:39"/> becauſe in ſlight caſes, they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally do very well; yet in more ſtubborn ones we are forced to have recourſe to more powerful penetrating ones.</p>
               <p>As for Alkalies, I don't be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that ever any one was cured by them of this Diſtemper, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I have known ſome Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that have taken a vaſt farrago of Teſtacious Powders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without any good effect at all, which afterwards has been done in a ſmall time, with a ſmall quantity of proper Acids.</p>
               <p>Before I conclud, I ſhall inſert a Preparation of Antimony, the which I have found of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary uſe, in the moſt inveterate Scurvies.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:42743:40"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take of white Flowers of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony eight ounces, Volatile Spirit of Tartar two pound, put them into a large Bolt-head, and digeſt in a gentle heat in</hi> Balneo, <hi>for fourteen days, then take out the Bolt-head and let it cool by degres, when cold, decant the clear Tincture from the Feces: Then put the decanted Liquor or Tincture into a long Cucurbite, fit a head to it exactly, and with a gentle fire, deſtill off the one half, the remaining part keep for uſe, in a Bottle well ſtopped with a glaſs ſtopper. That which comes over by Diſtillation, may be kept for the ſame uſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To make the Volatile Spirit of Tartar.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:42743:40"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take of very fine and clean Rheniſh Wine, Tartar twenty pound, put it into an Iron-pot, fit to the ſaid Pot, a Moors-head made either of Iron or Copper, the which fix to a large Worm fixed in a Tub of Water; fit a very large Recipient to the end of the Worm. Lute all the joynts except that of the Receiver, with very good Lute, and when the Lute is very well dried, make a very gentle fire under your Pot at firſt, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe by degrees, and continue as long as any thing will come over; then let the fire go out, undo your joynts and take out the</hi> Caput Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum; <hi>which Calcine to Greyneſs, in a large Crucible; then put three pound of the calcined</hi> Caput Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum <hi>into a long Cucurbite, then</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:42743:41"/> 
                  <hi>pour upon it, all the Spirit that came over, being before hand freed from the fetid Oyl that came over with it, by running through a Funnel, lined either with wet brown Paper, or Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton: Put on your Head, which lute very well with a wet Bladder, then put to a Receiver, which lute alſo very well, and with a moderate fire, draw off one half of the Spirit. Pour out that which remains in the Cucur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite as uſeleſs, and put in two pound more of the Calcined</hi> Caput Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum, <hi>upon which pour the Spirit before drawn off, and with a gentle fire draw off one half, whick keep for the aforeſaid uſe. It being a noble, volatile Spirit of Tartar, and is as noble a</hi> Menſtruum <hi>as moſt I have met with, not only for this uſe, but ſeveral others.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:42743:41"/>
               <p>Of the aforeſaid Tincture, I uſe to give about four, ſix, eight or ten drops, according to the age and ſtrength of my Patients, Morning and Evening, in about half a pint of ſtrong Infuſion or Decoction of Juniper Berries, without any precedent Purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; this Medicine performing that office, where there is occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; it anſwering every thing that is generally ſaid of a true Panacca; ſometimes working by Vomit, ſometimes by Stool, and ſometimes by Urine, but moſtly by a gentle Diaphoreſis or Sweating: And I have once known it to cauſe a Salivation, without any of the ill Symptoms that uſually attend it, when
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:42743:42"/> raiſed by Mercurial Medicines. Whoever hath a mind to ſee more of this Tincture, may read <hi>Glauber Op. Mineral. Par. Prim.</hi> from whom I had it, though I have ſomething varied from him. I have found it of great uſe, not only in the Scurvy, but many other Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Diſtempers, as Rheuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſms, Sciaticas, Dropſies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by ſome few Obſervations that I have made, I believe it may do great things even in the Gout it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Before I conclude, I ſhall mention one Objection more againſt my opinion, made to me by ſeveral, and that is, that a more than ordinary ſaltneſs,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:42743:42"/> is to be perceived in the Blood of Scorbutick Perſons, and this ſaltneſs they take to be an Acidity: But if they would but enquire a little narrowly into the matter, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of finding it to be an Acid ſaltneſs, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary they will find it to be, a Lixivious, Alkalious one.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:42743:43"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Gout.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Shall here make only ſome few Obſervations concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Gout, it being couſin German, to that of the Scurvy. Though I muſt confeſs the Gout to be a Diſtemper I have not had much to do with, but by that little I have ſeen of it, I am fully convinced, that it is not from Acids, as is general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, that, that troubleſome Diſtemper is occaſioned.</p>
               <p>I have obſerved conſiderable large Nodes, in which are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:42743:43"/> contained a hard chalky ſubſtance, and of which I have ſeen large quantities extracted, which by many experiments I have found to be as much an Alkaly, as either Crabs Eyes, Corral, Pearls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the which I ſuppoſe no man will deny.</p>
               <p>Now it being granted, that the matter contained in the aforeſaid Nodes, to be an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaly, how is it poſſible for this Diſtemper, to proceed from Acids, when in thoſe very parts where the Diſtemper moſt violently rages, there ſhould be produced ſuch large quantities of an Alkalious ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. For if the Diſtemper pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from Acids, as 'tis generally
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:42743:44"/> agreed upon, the Patient need not clog his Stomach with Alkalies as is generally pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, there being a Remedy already placed in the part af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected: And I verily believe, that the only reaſon why this Diſtemper has been accounted amongſt the <hi>Opprobria Medicorum,</hi> has been from the miſtaken Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they have had concerning it.</p>
               <p>But if men will ſtill perſiſt to aſſert, that this Diſtemper pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from Acids, and at the ſame time own the chalky ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance before-mentioned, which is only the Morbifick Matter indurated, to be an Alkaly, they muſt tacitely believe the Doctrine of Tranſmutation,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:42743:44"/> though openly they are aſhamed to own it, and will laugh at, and ridicule thoſe that do.</p>
               <p>But this is not all, for ſuppoſe the Acid Matter cauſing this Diſtemper to be tranſmuted into a chalky, alkalious ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the Diſtemper muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more pretend to come in or near the part, where this ſubſtance is lodged, it being placed as a Centry to guard it off: Nay, the Blood at times, muſt all, or at leaſt, great part of it, paſs through the Part or Parts, where this chalky ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is lodged, by which means a man would think, it ſhould be ſufficiently guarded from any more growing Acid;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:42743:45"/> and ſo by conſequence, when the chalky Nodes are once ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, people have not the leaſt reaſon for the future, to be in fear of the return of their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper: The contrary of which a great many honeſt Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to their ſorrows experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. So that a man would think, that theſe very Nodes alone, were ſufficient, if there were no other reaſons to be given for it, to ſatisfie any man, who is maſter of his reaſon, that Acids are not, and that Alkalies are, the cauſe of this Diſtemper. And if the Blood abound with too great a quantity of Alkalious Particles, the giving of Alkalies muſt be prepoſterous, is being to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:42743:45"/> add Fuel to the Flame, which inſtead of quenching or extinguiſhing, makes it ſo much the greater.</p>
               <p>It may not be amiſs to take notice, that few peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are troubled with the Gout, but thoſe who drink large quantities of Wine or ſome other generous Liquors, abounding with vinous Spirits; ſo that the Blood and other Juices, being impregnated with the ſaid vinous Spirits, theſe Spirits meeting with the volatile, alkalious Salt, of which, even the Blood of ſound Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is never deſtitute: By the means of which Salt, the vinous Spirit is coagulated,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:42743:46"/> and turned into that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (or ſomewhat like it) which <hi>Helmont</hi> calls his <hi>Offa Alba,</hi> which coagulated ſubſtance, not being capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of moving with the Blood and Juices through the ſmall Veſſels, cauſes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and violent pains, and in time, by the additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of other groſs, terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Particles, into the beforementioned chalky ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>By the foreſaid coagulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of vinous Spirits with the volatile Alkaly of the Blood, may a very good reaſon be given, for the Generation of the Stone in the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:42743:46"/> Bladder and Kidneys: And Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> tells us (being what <hi>Helmont</hi> had before done) that having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſome Stones of a certain Lythotomiſt, he put them into a Retort, and expoſed them to a ſtrong fire, and found that the better half conſiſted of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile, alkalious Salt, like unto that obtainable from Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Blood, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable quantity of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Oyl, ſo that it is plain, that the Generation of the Stone, is not from Acids, but Alkalies.</p>
               <p>From which may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, that it is not, from
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:42743:47"/> the Acidity of Rheniſh Wine, that makes the drinking of it pernicious to Gouty People, but from its abounding with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Particles, more than moſt other Wines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:42743:47"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Rheumatiſms.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THIS is another of the Diſtempers generally ſaid to proceed from Acids in the Blood; but very falſly, as I hope fully to make appear; I having had to do with multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes under this Diſtemper, and that (thanks to God) with very good ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>I. ſhall not trouble my ſelf to inveſtigate the original cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this Diſtemper, which are various, that being foreign to my deſign; but ſhall imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:42743:48"/> proceed to the buſineſs I have undertaken.</p>
               <p>Firſt of all; Having by the fire analyzed the Blood of Rheumatick Perſons, I have found it to abound more with Alkanious Particles, than that of ſound Perſons; but not the leaſt grain of any Acid ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in it; from which alone it may readily enough be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, That it proceeds not from Acids, but, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, from Alkalies.</p>
               <p>But it may be Objected, From whence proceeds that ſyzineſs and viſcoſity of the Serum, which is generally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the Blood of Rheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:42743:48"/> Perſons, if not from Acids? For we know that Milk, which is a ſort of Serum of the Blood, let it be in never ſo fluid a ſtate, by the addition of any Acid, though never ſo gentle, a great part of it will be immediately congulated and turned into Curds.</p>
               <p>To which I Anſwer, That the foreſaid Objection is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether invalid; the viſcouſneſs that is obſerved in the Serum of the Blood, being quite diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that of the Curds in Milk: Though there are thoſe ſubſtances contained in Milk, that are fit to make both Blood and Serum; but Milk is a much more compound liquor than
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:42743:49"/> the Serum of the Blood; ſo the compariſon being made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſubjects ſo vaſtly diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, it is of no validity at all.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe the compariſon between the two Liquors good; What agreement is there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Curds, and a ſubſtance like unto Gelly? None at all that I know of:</p>
               <p>But if inſtead of curdled Milk, they had made the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon between the inviſcated Serum and Hartſhorn Gelly, they had been in the right on't; for indeed I know not any two ſubjects more fit to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together. But then this compariſon will not in the leaſt prove the inviſcation of the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:42743:49"/> Serum to proceed from Acids, but on the contrary from Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalious Particles; for every body that knows what Harts-horn is, know that the reaſon of its ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Gelly, is from its abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with volatile alkalious Salts. And for the ſame reaſon it is, that Calves Feet, Izing-glaſs, Ivory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> make Gellies.</p>
               <p>By what I have ſaid, I hope, I have freed Acids from occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioning the viſcouſneſs of the Serum of the Blood in Rheu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiſms; which viſcoſity if it can be once taken off, every one knows that the Diſtemper immediately vaniſhes. But this is not to be done by Alkalies, that ever I could ſee, although
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:42743:50"/> I have given them in large quantities. But it is expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly to be done by proper Acids, ſuch as the before-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Tincture of Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Calibiats.</p>
               <p>But here I expect that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will think that I have caught my ſelf in a trap, when I bring in Calibiats amongſt the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Acids, when they are generally owned by all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to be Alkalies; to confirm the truth of which, they tell you it is plainly manifeſt, that filings of Iron will make as great an Efferveſcency with all ſorts of Acids, as any of the Alkalies I have mentioned; therefore it is plain I muſt be
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:42743:50"/> much in the wrong, in reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Calibiats amongſt the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Acids.</p>
               <p>From this difficulty I ſhall endeavour to extricate my ſelf, and likewiſe to prove, That Iron or Steel, until it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into a Vitriol (and every body will allow Vitriol to be an Acid) cannot act upon the Blood or Serum to cauſe any alteration in it, nor ſo much as any way enter into the Veins or Arteries.</p>
               <p>It is the Cuſtom of Skilful Practitioners, before they give Steel Medicines, to enquire of their Patients, Whether they are ſenſible of any Acidity in their Stomachs; in which part
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:42743:51"/> I do allow Acids oftentimes to abound, and that exorbitantly. If they are ſenſible of any Acidity there, it is then found neceſſary to give Iron or Steel, without any Preparation at all, by reaſon that by the means of the Acids in the Stomach, it is turned into a Vitriol, and ſo made capable of being carri'd into the Blood, whereas in ſuch caſes, if it hath been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſatiated by a precedent Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, it hath little or no effect at all. On the other hand, if there be no ſenſible Acidity in the Stomach, Iron or Steel being given Unprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, are carri'd off by Stool, without the leaſt alteration, or
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:42743:51"/> any part of it being admitted into the Blood.</p>
               <p>All or moſt of the Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Steel that I know of, that are good for any thing, are performed by the means of Acids, which tend to the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of their parts, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into a Vitriol. Now according to the difference of the Acids uſed, the reſult is a different ſort of Vitriol, which hath different operations: But on the contrary, Alkalies do ſo lock up the Body of Iron, as to make it unfit to be taken as Medicine, by reaſon of its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary hardneſs and firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Texture.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:42743:52"/>
               <p>The Preparations of Steel I generally uſe are, that which goes by the name of Dr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi>'s Preparation of Steel, and is now almoſt every where to be had; which altho it be grown common, is, for all that, no deſpicable Medicine; and that which follows.
<q>
                     <p>Take of filings of Steel, or rather Iron, very clean and free from duſt, one pound and half, <hi>Sal Armoniac</hi> two pound; make the <hi>Sal Armoniac</hi> into very fine Powder, then mix them well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in an iron or ſtone Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, then put the mixture into a moiſt Cellar, and let it ſtand a week. Then put it into a very
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:42743:52"/> large Crucible, which cover with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> piece of Tile, afterwards put the Crucible into a Charcoal Fire, which increaſe by degrees, till the Crucible be almoſt red hot; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it has continued in this ſtate about an hour, take away the Fire, and let your calcined mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cool by degrees; when cold, take it out of the Crucible, and make into fine Powder in a glaſs or ſtone Mortar, then put it into a Bottle with a wide mouth, which ſtop with a glaſs Stopple, and keep in a warm place.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe two Preparations pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly given, and with conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient Vehicles, I have known
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:42743:53"/> of very great uſe in Rheuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſms. And the laſt, when all other Medicines have proved ineffectual, has never once fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me in the moſt inveterate Obſtructions of the <hi>Menſes</hi> in Women.</p>
               <p>Beſides the forementioned Preparations of Steel, I have frequently found Cinnaber of Antimony, or even common Cinnaber, mixt with a due proportion of <hi>Gum Guaiaci,</hi> and given in large quantities, to be of great uſe, not only in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed Rheumatiſms, but even in Sciatica's of long ſtanding, by the means of which alone I have known many cured.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:42743:53"/>
               <p>I did formerly believe Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naber of Antimony, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cinnaber to be Alkalies; but ſince I have more nicely inquired into it, I find that by a peculiar management, a large quantity of an acid ſulphuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Spirit may be obtained from it.</p>
               <p>Before I conclude upon this Head, it will not, I ſuppoſe, be amiſs, to obſerve one thing more about the Preparation of Steel before-mention'd, and that is, that whilſt it is kept dry, and in a Powder, it is one of the greateſt Deoppilatives or openers of Obſtructions ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable: But let it be put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Cellar, and run <hi>per deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium,</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:42743:54"/> which it will do in a few days, fifty or ſixty drops of the ſaid Oil <hi>per deliquium,</hi> given twice a day in a ſtrong De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of Oak Bark, I have of late found never to fail me in ſtopping a ſeminal Flux, which all People will allow has hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been found as difficult a thing to do as any whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. Some People having told me, that they ſuppoſed the Stipticity to proceed from the Decoction of Oak Bark only, I have purpoſely tried it alone, and altho I own Oak Bark to be a Noble Stiptic, and to do Wonders, the Decoction being taken in at the mouth, and by way of Clyſter, in common,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:42743:54"/> ſimple Diarrhea's, and even ſometimes in bloody Fluxes; yet in the caſe before-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned it would do nothing at all; but adding ſome drops of the Oil of <hi>Mars</hi> to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, it had ſoon the deſired effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:42743:55"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Conſumptions.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Have little to ſay upon this Subject, but that I have ſeen great numbers of People under this Circumſtance, to whom have been given large quantities of Alkalies, and all ſorts of Balſamics, and thoſe things called Pectorals, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt advantage in the world; tho I have ſeen others who have had the manifeſt ſigns of a confirmed <hi>Phtiſis</hi> or Conſumption, who by the plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful uſe of proper Acids, have
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:42743:55"/> been reduced from a ſtate of dying, to that of perfect health.</p>
               <p>My Reaſons in ſhort, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my beſt Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for the uſe of Acids, and the diſuſe of Alkalies, are as follow.</p>
               <p>The Globules of the Blood by reaſon of ſo great a quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Acrid, Alkalious, Lixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Particles, being mixed with it, being broken and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedly mix'd with the Serum are, together with the Serum, admitted into the ſmall Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dules of the Lungs, and not being capable of being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd, cauſe Inflamations there, and by conſequence Hectick Fevers, which always precede and accompany a
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:42743:56"/> Pthiſis or Conſumption. Now by the uſe of Alkalies and Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamicks, theſe extravaſated Globules are ſo far from being thrown out, and the depraved ſtate of the Blood from being altered, that inſtead of it, the ſtate of the Blood is made much worſe by Alkalies; and by Balſamicks the Puſtles oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned from the extravaſated Globules being admitted into the ſmall Glandules, are brought to Suppuration, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary conſequence of which is an Ulceration, and when ſo tender a part as the Lungs are, is once Ulcerated, he muſt ſhew himſelf an Artiſt indeed that can heal ſuch Ulcers.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:42743:56"/>
               <p>Now proper Acids being given in due time, confirm the Texture of the Blood, and reduce the Serum to a ſtate of fluidity, by which means the Fever and Inflamation of the Lungs are taken off, and the extravaſated Globules of Blood, by means of a thin Serum, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by its quick motion in that part, when in a fluid ſtate, are by degrees carried off, and ſo the Puſtles diſappear.</p>
               <p>But it may be Objected, How comes it to paſs, that the broken Globules of Blood, you ſo often mention, come to be admitted along with the Serum into the Glands of ſeveral parts, and that they cannot by the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:42743:57"/> ſame reaſon be carried off to the parts deſigned, along with the Serum or Lympha, as it is ſtiled, when it once comes into the Lymphatick Veſſels?</p>
               <p>To which I Anſwer, That when they are firſt admitted into the Glands, I mean the broken Globules, coming juſt out of the extremities of the Arteries, and being then very hot, the ſides of them are lax, and ſo in ſome meaſure capable of being compreſſed or ſqueez'd together; but being once ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the Glands, the motion of the Serum from them, through the Lymphatick Veſſels, being very ſlow, they ſoon grow cool, and ſo more
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:42743:57"/> firm; and by reaſon of the different figure of theſe broken Globules from the Pores, by which the Serum is to paſs from the Glands to the Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatick Veſſels, they are not ſuffered to paſs through with the Serum, as in the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned inſtance of the mixture of Oyl and Water, ſo that the Globules being extravaſated and without motion, corrupt; from which corruption pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds all the ill ſymptons I have mentioned to accrue from the broken Globules of the Blood being admitted into the Glands.</p>
               <p>But to return to the buſineſs of Acids; to confirm the truth
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:42743:58"/> of what I have ſaid, beſides my own Obſervations, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Riverius,</hi> that famous Practitioner, ſomewhere ſays, That he hath ſeveral times cured a confirmed Pthiſis or Conſumption, by giving only of large quantities of Conſerve of Red Roſes, well Acidulated with Oil of Sulphur <hi>per Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now I am ſpeaking of Oil of Sulphur <hi>per Campanam,</hi> give me leave to add an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that <hi>Helmont</hi> gives of it in his <hi>Arbor Vitae;</hi> which altho it hath not any immediate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Point in hand, yet may be pertinent enough to ſhew the good effects of Acids,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:42743:58"/> in keeping the Blood in a good Texture, and by that means prolonging Life, and preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us from Diſeaſes. <hi>Moſes,</hi> who perhaps underſtood the Myſteries of Nature as well as any man, and who was guided by an unerring, infallible Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſays, that in the Blood is contained the Life. Now the Texture of the Blood being confirmed, and its Globules whole, muſt go a great way towards the prolongation of Life: But on the contrary, the Texture of the Blood being ſpoiled, and its Globules bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, (which they are by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalies) muſt in great meaſure ſhorten Life, and occaſion Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:42743:59"/>
               <p>In the Year 1600. ſays <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> a certain Military Man, being burthen'd with a great number of ſmall Children, made his Complaint to me that he was 58 years of age, and that if he ſhould chance to die, his Children muſt go begging from door to door. He ask'd of me ſomething, whereby his Life might be preſerved. I being then a Young Man, and commiſerating his Condition, I conſidered with my ſelf, that a lighted Match of Brimſtone would preſerve Wine from Corruption; therefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with my ſelf, that the Acid Oil of Sulphur did neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily ſo contain this Flame of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:42743:59"/> Sulphur, and all the Smell of it, that it ſelf was nothing elſe, meaning the Acid Spirit or Oil, but the Fume of Sulphur it ſelf, imbibed by its Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Salt. Laſt of all, I was confirmed that the Blood was the Wine of our Lives, and that being preſerved, if it did not occaſion long Life, it would at leaſt in ſome meaſure be prolonged, by our being guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Diſeaſes, and free from Pains. Wherefore I gave him a Pot full of the Diſtilled Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor or Oil of Sulphur, and likewiſe taught him the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Diſtilling the ſaid Oil from kindled Brimſtone. I furthermore bid him, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:42743:60"/> Meal, in the firſt draught of Beer he drank, that he ſhould take two drops of the ſaid Liquor, and by no means ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed it; I being ſatisfied that two drops did contain a large quantity of the Fume of Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur. The Man followed my advice, and at this time walks about the Streets of <hi>Bruxels,</hi> being Sixteen hundred forty one: And which is more than all, for the whole Forty years he never laboured under any Diſtemper, although once by a Fall upon the Ice, he broke his Leg near the Knee, yet all the time he was under Cure, he was free from a Fever. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſlender and lean, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:42743:60"/> although in want of all Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, lived to be thus Old. The Name of this Old Man is <hi>John Maſs,</hi> who ſerved in the Bed-Chamber of the Biſhop of <hi>Ypre,</hi> when Count <hi>Egmont</hi> and <hi>Horne</hi> were beheaded, and was at that time Twenty five years of age.</p>
               <p>The Truth of this Relation need not in the leaſt be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Man being alive and well when it was wrote. By which Inſtance it is plain, that Acids are not the Cauſe of Diſeaſes, but Preſervatives a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; and whatever is a Preſervative from Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, by the ſame parity of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt be of uſe to repel
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:42743:61"/> them, when we labour under them.</p>
               <p>A ſignal Inſtance of which, I remember I have ſomewhere read of a Perſon who purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffered himſelf to be bitten by a Viper, in order to try the good Effects of Monſieur <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi>'s Volatile Alkalious Salt of the ſame Animal, in preventing and taking off the Symptoms that attend the Biting of the ſaid Creature. The Volatile Salt and other Antidotes were in large quantities given, but all in vain; for inſtead of allay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Symptoms ſo increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that nothing leſs was to be feared, than the loſs of the poor Man's Life. To the beſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:42743:61"/> of my remembrance, nay, I think I may be poſitive, that it was in the Wriſt where he was bitten; but for all the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile Salts, and other Antidotes, in a very little time his Arm was ſwelled ſo big, and ſo high, that Amputation could do him no ſervice; nay, all the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanders, which were many, gave him up for dead. At laſt a certain Perſon adviſed the giving of him large quantities of only ſo ſimple an Acid as Juice of Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons; which immediately abated the Symptoms, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieved him from all manner of Danger.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:42743:62"/>
               <p>We live in an inquiſitive Age, wherein People have more ſenſe than to take things upon truſt: The obtaining of the Blood, both of well and diſtemper'd Perſons, is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult matter; and I deſire no greater juſtice to be done me, than that People would them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Experiment the truth of what I have ſaid: And if after trial it be found that the Blood of perſons in any of the before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned caſes, hath any thing of Acid in it, I will own my ſelf in the wrong. But ſhall never take the leaſt notice of ſuch ſcurrilous Anſwers as I have been uſed to, nothing of that nature being in the leaſt
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:42743:62"/> valid with me, that is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by well-atteſted Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The CONCLUSION.</head>
               <p>IT is, I ſuppoſe, allowed by every body, that Sea-Salt is an Acid, and for that very reaſon only it is, that we who eat ſuch large quantities of Fleſh are not able to live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it. For all ſorts of Fleſh abounding with large quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of volatile Alkalious Salts, if the ſaid Alkalious Salts were in ſome meaſure locked up and mortified by the means of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:42743:63"/> Sea Salt, or which is all one, that which is the product of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Brine-pits, they having their ſaltneſs from the ſame origine, which is Currents of Water paſſing through great Rocks of Salt; which late diſcoveries have made appear to be both in <hi>England</hi> and many other parts of the World: As for inſtance, one in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> whoſe Vein is Twenty Yards thick, and may be traced for a great many Miles together; which very Rock alone is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to Impregnate almoſt an Ocean of Waters.</p>
               <p>There is ſome reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That the People before the Flood did not eat Fleſh,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:42743:63"/> but liv'd altogether upon Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables, as Fruits, Herbs, and Roots; which, I ſuppoſe, was one great reaſon of their Longe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity. And it may be obſerved that in <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countries abounding with Fruit, the People are longer Liv'd than in thoſe Countries that want them. Now had the Antedeluvian People eaten Fleſh as we do now, I can't imagine what they would have done for Salt; for ſuppoſing Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Hypotheſis true, (the which I think there is not the leaſt reaſon to doubt of, his Arguments to prove it being to me Unanſwerable) I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their Rivers muſt have
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:42743:64"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:42743:64"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:42743:65"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:42743:65"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:42743:66"/> been altogether void of ſalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and how they could come at ſalt any other way, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the ſtate of their Earth, I can't imagine: And for them to have eaten Meat without Salt, muſt neceſſarily have greatly prejudic'd their healths, and ſhortned their lives. For we have ſeen in the late <hi>Iriſh</hi> Wars what deſtruction and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation was made in our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my by eating Meat without Salt, of which at one time there was a ſcarcity, whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments having been ſwept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way together with Fevers and Fluxes. But the Antedeluvian People living upon Vegetables, they had no need of Salt, there
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:42743:66"/> being a ſufficient quantity of Acidity in them to confirm the Texture of their Blood, and preſerve them from Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>Since I have been mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sea Salt, I ſhall make bold to trouble you with a relation of a ſtrange and accidental Cure wrought upon a Perſon in a Tympanitis, given over as Incurable by the moſt eminent Phyſicians of <hi>England,</hi> by barely immerging her two or three times over Head in Sea Water.</p>
               <p>The Perſon was Daughter to an Eminent Citizen of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> ſhe had labour'd under a Tympanitis Three or Four years; her Father applied
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:42743:67"/> himſelf to moſt of the Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Phyſicians for advice, but all that they could do ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified nothing. Her Father who is a Corpulent man, has ſeveral times told me, that her <hi>Abdomen</hi> was ſwelled ſo big, that his Cloak would not lap round her, and ſhe was then not above Ten years of Age. It happened one Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that her Mother, Two Brothers, her ſelf, and a Maid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant, were Bitten by a little Dog they had in the Houſe, which was grown Mad. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice was preſently given by Dr. <hi>Johnſon,</hi> an Eminent Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician then living in <hi>Worceſter,</hi> That they ſhould all go to the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:42743:67"/> Salt-Waters to be dipp'd; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve by the way, the efficacy of Salt-Waters in preventing the dreadful ſymptoms that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend thoſe People Bitten by Mad Dogs: The Mother, her Two Sons, and Maid-ſervant, were prepared to go, but ſhe did not deſign to take her Daughter with her, ſuppoſing her not capable of living till ſhe came to the Journeys end. The poor diſtreſſed Child ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them all going away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her, called to her Father, telling him, He took care of every body elſe, but valued not what became of her; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which her Father being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with compaſſion, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:42743:68"/> ſhe ſhould go, let the event be what it would. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly ſhe was carried down, and when it came to her turn to be dipped, it was as much as two men could do to immerge her over Head: After they were all dipped, they were carried to an adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Houſe and put to Bed; ſhe had not been in Bed many Hours, but ſhe called for a Pot, and piſſed ſeveral Quarts, even more at that one time, than ſhe had done of ſome Months before; and when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Worceſter,</hi> which was within few days, ſhe run out of the Boat herſelf to her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without any help, when
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:42743:68"/> ſhe had not been able ſo much as to ſtand of a year or two be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. To be ſhort, without any other help, ſhe was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly cured of her Tympanitis, and is now a Tall, Slender, Healthy Woman, as any I know.</p>
               <p>I have mentioned this thing becauſe I find it not any where taken notice off, and may be of ſervice to others. Nay, I am told that a certain obſcure Perſon in <hi>Herefordſhire,</hi> has Cured ſeveral by the ſame me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, to his own great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and withal ſays, that it never once failed him.</p>
               <p>I muſt beg the Lady's par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for writing this Relation
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:42743:69"/> without firſt asking her leave; but ſince I have no other end in it but to ſerve Mankind, I doubt not but I ſhall be eaſily excuſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Helmont</hi> poſitively ſays, and as I my ſelf have found it true, That Spirit of Sea Salt, which is an exalted Acid, is a certain Remedy in the Strangury; which is a Diſtemper general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid to proceed from Acids; which if it doth, inſtead of being Cured it muſt be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Exaſperated by Spirit of Salt, the contrary of which I have frequently Experimented. <hi>Helmont</hi> ſomewhere elſe ſays of it, <hi>Eſt namque Acidiſſimus, nec ſibi par habet remedium extinguen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis</hi>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:42743:69"/> 
                  <hi>ardoribus Urine, etiam preſente in Veſſica Calculo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I remember that not long ſince an Eminent Phyſician told me, That bare Juice of Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons would ſooner take off the Heat of Urine, in People that are, as we commonly call it, Clapp'd, than Emulſions, or any of the things commonly uſed; which ſince I have found true; and have alſo found that the Urine of ſuch Perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds more with Volatile Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalious Salt, than that of ſound People: Upon which I have been induced to try, whether the Acid Spirit of <hi>Guaiacum,</hi> which that Wood affords in large quantities, would not
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:42743:70"/> be more prevalent in the Cure of confirmed Poxes, than the bare Infuſion or Decoction of the ſaid Wood; the which in conjunction with Cinnaber of Antimony, or common Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naber, and Gum <hi>Guaiaci,</hi> or elſe with the before mentioned Tincture of Antimony, has ſeldom failed me in Curing the moſt confirmed Poxes without Salivation.</p>
               <p>I am very apt to believe, that if the rectified Acid Spirits, obtainable from moſt, if not all Woods, were made uſe of, they would be found to be great Specificks in moſt Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, eſpecially Chronical ones.</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:42743:70"/>
               <p>And ſince I have mentioned Specificks, I do own that it may be rationally enough Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, That my Doctrine of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cids does mightily thwart with that of Specificks; ſince there are many Specificks that are neither Alkalies nor Acids, yet ſeldom fail of Curing Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, as rationally to be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to proceed from Alkalious Particles abounding, as any whatſoever.</p>
               <p>To which I Anſwer, That I have only brought my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Acids upon the Stage, as a general one, in oppoſition to the general and pernicious Doctrine of Alkalies. For ſhould I deny the Doctrine of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:42743:71"/> Specificks, I muſt deny matter of fact, which is what I ſhall never do, till I am totally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of my Reaſon.</p>
               <p>There is a little Herb called <hi>Paronichia cum foliis Rutaceis,</hi> or Whitlow Graſs, with leaves like Rew; the which the Honourable Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends as a Specifick in the King's Evil: Which Herb I have immerged both in mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately Acid and Alkalious Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, yet could not perceive any Luctus or Efferveſcency; yet I have known it do wonders in the forementioned Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and that without having the leaſt ſenſible Operation: I ſhall inſtance in one particular.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:42743:71"/>
               <p>A poor Woman in <hi>Worceſter</hi> having one only Child of about Ten years of Age, who by Weaving of Bone-lace main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained both her Mother and her ſelf: The Mother of the Child came one day to me making a great complaint that ſhe was undone? I asked her the cauſe of her complaint; ſhe told me, her Child who kept her in her old Age from Begging, had for Two Years had Scrophulous Tumors in and about her Privities, and that about Three Months be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, one of the ſaid Tumors began to Ulcerate, and that now the Ulcers were crept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her Body, which made her
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:42743:72"/> uneapable of Sitting. I went immediately with the poor Woman to ſee her Daughter, and found what ſhe ſaid was true, the poor Girl being the moſt miſerable ſpectacle I ever ſaw. I remembring what Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> had ſaid concerning <hi>Paronychia;</hi> and being ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſatisfied that there was not the leaſt reaſon of doubting the truth of any thing he had ſaid, when he related it as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact upon his own Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; I was reſolved to try it upon this Girl; I firſt of all Purged her Three or Four times with <hi>Calamelanos, Rezin</hi> of <hi>Jallap,</hi> and <hi>Cremor Tartar;</hi> I afterwards gave her Two large
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:42743:72"/> Handfuls of the ſaid Herb dried, ordering her to put it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Two Gallons of ſmall Beer after it had done working, and let it ſtand Six Days, and then to drink it for her conſtant Drink: She continued to take it for about Two Months, in which time, without applying any thing to the Ulcers, ſave Clean Cloths, both Ulcers and Tumors vaniſhed, and ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued well till I left <hi>Worceſter,</hi> which was two years after the Cure was performed, and is ſo ſtill for ought I can hear, I having ſeveral times enquired after her.</p>
               <p>Another Inſtance of the Operation of Specificks, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:42743:73"/> their being either Alkalies or Acids, is that frequently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented Decoction of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> after having been Boyled for a conſiderable time in Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, has been found not to have loſt the leaſt Grain of its former Weight, or imparting either Taſte or Colour to the Water; yet this Water in which the Mercury has been De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted, has not failed of killing and bringing away Worms, when other Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Medicines have failed.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe <hi>Crocus Mettalorum,</hi> and ſome other Preparations of Antimony, being barely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed in Wine, without loſing the leaſt Grain of their Weight,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:42743:73"/> or imparting either Smell, Taſte, or Colour, to the Wine in which they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, yet never fail of giving the Wine a violently Emettick Quality. I my ſelf have at ſeveral times poured above Twenty Quarts of Canary upon one and the ſame Ounce of <hi>Crocus Mettalorum</hi> Powdered, and found that the laſt Quart, was as violently Emettick as the firſt; altho after nice trial I could not find that the Powder was diminiſhed one Grain in its Weight, or had, as is before-obſerved, cauſed the leaſt ſenſible Alteration in the Wine.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:42743:74"/>
               <p>The <hi>Cortex,</hi> that Noble Specifick in all Intermitting Fevers, I don't apprehend to perform its office as it is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Alkaly or Acid; though being mix'd with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cids, it performs its work much better than without them.</p>
               <p>It is a general complaint againſt that Noble Medicine, and is the only occaſion of deterring ſome People from the uſe of it, That being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in never ſo large quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, eſpecially in Quartans, it only puts off the Fit for a time, but does not totally eradicate the Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, it returning after a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:42743:74"/> period. To obviate which inconvenience; I have been adviſed to give it after the following manner, which ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or never fails of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the return of the Diſtemper.</p>
               <p>Two Hours before the Fit, I give a gentle Emet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick; after that has done Working, an Opiate; when the Fit is over, I give the quantity of a large Nutmeg of the following Electuary with the Decoction, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat it every Four Hours, for Five or Six Days, order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Patients to eat ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of eaſy Digeſtion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in an Hour after each Doſe:
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:42743:75"/> After the expiration of Five or Six Days, I give it only firſt in the Morning, and at Five in the Afternoon for a Week, Eating ſomething af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter each Doſe.
<q>
                     <p>Take of Pick'd <hi>Peruvian</hi> Bark One Ounce, make it into a very fine Powder, and with good Syrup of Lemons, as much as is ſufficient, make an Electua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Immediately after each Doſe of which, I give about a Quarter of a Pint of the following Decoction:
<q>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:42743:75"/>
                     <p>Take of Pick'd <hi>Peruvian</hi> Bark Half an Ounce, <hi>Gentian</hi> Roots Two Drams, <hi>Centaury</hi> Two Pugils, Spring-Water Two Quarts; Boyl to the Conſumption of One Half, when Cold ſtrain out and keep for uſe.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>By this Method, I have known Three or Four Ounces of the <hi>Cortex</hi> perfectly Cure Quartans without any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe, after People have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a Pound or more after the common Method, which has only put by the Fits for a time.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:42743:76"/>
               <p>The Reaſons, as I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, why this method of giving the <hi>Cortex</hi> ſhould be more prevalent than that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly taken, are, the Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the <hi>Cortex</hi> being very firm, the Medicine being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and the Patient Faſting Three or Four Hours after it, it ſlides out of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack into the ſmall Guts, and ſo on; the ſmall Guts being empty, there is not preſſure enough to ſqueeze but a very ſmall quantity of it into the Lacteal Veſſels; ſo that the greateſt quantity of it is carried away as Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crement: But the Patient eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomething of eaſy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:42743:76"/> within ſo ſmall a time as an Hour after it, that eaten, is turned into <hi>Chyle</hi> before tho Particles of the <hi>Cortex</hi> can be carried off, and the <hi>Chyle</hi> being of a Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous Nature, retains the ſmall Particles, and carries them along with it into the Blood; ſo that the Blood is more impregnated by one Doſe this way given, than with Twenty Doſes without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently eating after it.</p>
               <p>As a confirmation of the truth of what I have ſaid concerning the firmneſs of the Texture of the Particles of the <hi>Cortex;</hi> if you boyl it never ſo well, the clear De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:42743:77"/> will not Gure a <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidian</hi> or <hi>Tertian</hi> Ague; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the <hi>Cortex</hi> after it hath been well Boiled, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to Powder, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven after the foreſaid man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, will cure a <hi>Quartan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would be a great Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the Commonwealth of Phyſick, if there were a faithful Record kept of all the Cures wrought by Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Medicines, by which means Phyſicians might ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to a certainty of Curing more Diſtempers than that of Agues; which thing I never expect to ſee, ſo long as te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious nonſenſical Compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are depended on.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:42743:77"/>
               <p>I don't remember that any of the Ancient or Modern Botannick Writers, have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned the Leaves of <hi>Aſſara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacca</hi> to have any other qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity beſides that of a violent Purger by Vomit and Stool: But Mr. <hi>Pitt,</hi> a late Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and Learned Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> my ſingular good Friend, told me, that he found it to be one of the moſt noble Purgers of the Head, that he ever met with, having a different Operation from any other Medicine that he ever met with; that the Snuffing up of Three, Four, or Five Grains of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the dried Leaves at
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:42743:78"/> Night going to Bed, would on the Morrow, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flurbing reſt that Night, but rather cauſing it, occaſion the diſcharge of a vaſt quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Serous Matter from the Glands of the Noſe; nay would ſometimes laſt for Two or Three Days, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the leaſt a Sternuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</p>
               <p>By the repeated uſe of this Powder alone, I have known the moſt violent, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed Head Aches imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble taken off, after they have eluded the efficacy of the moſt Noble Celebrated Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalicks: But this ought to be taken notice of, That
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:42743:78"/> whoever takes this Medicine muſt confine themſelves to their Houſes, and keep as warm as if they had taken the moſt violent Purge.</p>
               <p>I have been told by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Gentleman, who uſes a great quantity of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this Herb amongſt his poor Neighbours after the aforeſaid manner, that he was once induced to uſe it in a Deafneſs of long ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; he gave the Patient Four or Five Grains to Snuff up into each Noſtril every Fourth or Fifth Night, and ordered that Three Grains ſhould every Night with a Quill be blown into each Ear; and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:42743:79"/> in a Fortnight's time the Party recovered his Hearing as well as ever in his Life.</p>
               <p>I could expatiate a great deal more concerning ſimple Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick Remedies. But what I have already ſaid is enough to ſatisfie the World, that I allow the Doctrine of Specificks; nay I think it ought to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented that it is not more Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated.</p>
               <p>I have been told by ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Perſons, who have much converſed with the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of <hi>Weſt-India,</hi> that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Specificks is mightily Cultivated by thoſe Barbarous People, by which means they have arrived to a certainty in
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:42743:79"/> Curing moſt Diſtempers, and that to ſee People of One hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty and a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and thirty Years of Age, is as common a ſight, as in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to ſee People of Sixty. Now what a ſhame is it for us, who live in a Learned and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive Age, to be outdone by thoſe Barbarous and Illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate People; nay, for ought I know, the greateſt part of our Skill we had from them, or a People altogether as Ignorant.</p>
               <p>The Phyſicians of <hi>Europe</hi> are not arrived to ſo great a certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in any one thing, as in the Cure of Agues; And who may we thank for that but the Poor <hi>Indians,</hi> who imparted to
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:42743:80"/> us the uſe of their famous Bark?</p>
               <p>From whom had <hi>Hypocrates,</hi> that Father of Phyſicians, his Skill, but by Collecting the common Obſervations; the which only it was that made him ſo very famous throughout the World. But the ſtate of Nature being in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure altered in that long track of time ſince he lived, and the difference of our Climate from that wherein he lived, makes that his Obſervations don't al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together hold good with us. So that if we will arrive to any certainty in our Art, we muſt make nice Obſervations of our own.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:42743:80"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Helmont</hi> in his Treatiſe of Fevers ſays, <hi>Quiſ que Artificum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, quod promittit, Statuarius nempe Statuam, Calciarius Calcios indubiè parat, ſolus autem Medicus nil au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det ex arte ſpondere ſuâ, quia Niti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Fundamentis incertis, per acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens duntaxat, ſubinde, atque do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losè proficuus.</hi> Which in <hi>Engliſh</hi> is, That there is a certainty in all Profeſſions, but that of a Phyſician; and it is altogether our own faults, for want of due Obſervation, that we act upon ſuch uncertainties as we do.</p>
               <p>But to return to the buſineſs of Acids; What great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit does Mankind, in general, receive from Mineral Spring-Waters?
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:42743:81"/> All of which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to be Acids; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the difference of the Acid contained in them, they have different Operations. Some of them, as <hi>Acton, Epſome, Dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidge, Northall,</hi> &amp;c. abounding with Aluminous, as well as Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triolick Particles, work by Stool. Others, as <hi>Tunbridge, Aſtrop, Ilmington,</hi> &amp;c. Abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Vitriolick Particles only, are Alteratives, and are generally carried off by Urine. The <hi>Bath</hi>-Waters, abounding with Nitro-Sulphureous Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, have a different Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from any of the former, but are generally carried off by Urine, tho ſometimes by ſweat.</p>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:42743:81"/>
               <p>There is ſcarce a Perſon la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring under any Chronical Diſtemper, or ill habit of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, (whoſe Fortune or Buſineſs will permit them) but at the proper ſeaſon are ſent to one of the forementioned Places; and I verily believe, to our no great Credit, that more Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are freed from Chronical Diſtempers by the uſe of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Waters, than by all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Preſcriptions: Though I am very well ſatisfied, that Mineral Waters, not being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly taken, do frequently a great deal of miſchief.</p>
               <p>Beſides the ſervice done to Mankind by drinking of Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Waters, what advantage does
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:42743:82"/> accrue to many People labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under ſome ſort of Nervous Diſtempers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by merely Bathing themſelves in the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro-Sulphureous Hot Baths.</p>
               <p>There is alſo a new way of Sweating, by the means of the Volatile Acid Steams ariſing from the evaporating Brine, in the making of Salt at our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Salt-pits, lately invented by Mr. <hi>Henry Hodges</hi> of <hi>Droyt-Wych</hi> in <hi>Worceſterſhire,</hi> by the means of which, ſeveral very great things have been done, even in caſes where the Bath, Common Hummums and Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio's, have proved altogether ineffectual. I am ſorry that I am at a place where I cannot
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:42743:82"/> procure a number of Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to inſert in this place, which might be of ſervice to Mankind: But to ſupply the place of them, I ſhall add ſomething done in a little Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Houſe I erected of my own, wherein I imitated, if not out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did, the way of Sweating at <hi>Droyt-Wych;</hi> but my many Avo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations hindred me from the proſecuting of it.</p>
               <p>I procured a quantity of the Virgin Salt, from the Salt-Rock in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> and as I had occaſion, I diſſolved a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient quantity of it in Spring-Water, making a Brine as ſtrong as that obtainable from the Brine-Pits; with this Brine
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:42743:83"/> I filled a large Iron Pot, which had Pipes of Wood went from it to a little Room over head, made convenient for People to Sweat in: Under my Pot I made a fire, which both warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Room and made the Brine to boyl, and from the boyling Brine aroſe ſuch quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Steams as filled my Room, which, when it was warmed and full of ſteams, was fit for uſe: I had, beſide the large Pipes which ſupplied the whole Room, ſeveral others of different lengths, by the means of which I more forcibly conveyed the Steams to any particular part. By this way of Sweating, I have known a
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:42743:83"/> Gentlewoman Cured, as wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alſo one at <hi>Droyt-Wych,</hi> of an Inveterate Leproſy, which had eluded the Efficacy of all other Medicines and Baths. It rarely failed taking off the moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Old Aches and Pains. In all Relaxations of the Nerves and Tendons, I have never met with any thing compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to it. To be ſhort, I found it as good as the <hi>Bath</hi> in moſt things, and in many out-did it; and I believe Mr. <hi>Hodges,</hi> computing the time he has uſed the way of Sweating at his Brine-Pits, and the number of People he has had, can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a greater Catalogue, and more conſiderable Cures
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:42743:84"/> wrought, than hath been at the <hi>Bath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I hope by the means of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimental Philoſophy, ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily begun and encouraged by that Admirable and never-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently to be valued Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> to ſee the Art of Phyſick arrive to as great Certainty and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as other Arts and Sciences are arrived to. For, as I before obſerved, by Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mically Analyzing the Blood and Juices, both in their Natural and Morbid ſtate, we may arrive to ſome certainty in the Knowledge of the Cauſe of Diſtempers; which I am afraid we have hitherto been greatly ignorant of; and when
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:42743:84"/> once the Cauſes of Diſtempers are throughly known, the Cure of them will be no difficult matter.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude in the Words of that Induſtrious Philoſopher by the Fire, <hi>Helmont,</hi> in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe <hi>De Lichiaſi: In noſtris furnis le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimus, non eſſe in Natura certius Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endi genus ad cognoſcendum per cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas radicales &amp; conſtitutivas rerum; quamdum Scitur quid, quantumque in re quaque ſit contentum. Ita quidem ut cognitio &amp; connexio cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarum, non conſtent clarius, quam cum res ipſas ita recluſeris, ut co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram prodeant ac velut tecum loquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Siquidem entia realia, dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat ſtantia, in ſuis primor dialibus,</hi>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:42743:85"/> 
                  <hi>&amp; ſuccedentibus ſeminum Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius, adeoque in verâ entitate Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiali dant notitiam &amp; proferunt cauſam cognoſcendi Naturam Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Mediorum &amp; extremitatum. Quippe ſunt cauſa generationis, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtentiae &amp; permutationis, ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ipſorum radicem, quoniam (teſte Raimundo) utcunque Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus habeat profundum ingenium Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentabile, aut Naturale, de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus extrinſecis: tamen nunquam per aliquam rationem quae venit ad ſenſum, poterit directè cognoſcere, nec judicari, cum quali natura, aut virtute, per fortitudinem intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, habeat Multiplicatio grani, creſcere ſuper terram, niſi pro ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudinario, ab obſervatione de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpto. Nec ſciet unquam, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo</hi>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:42743:85"/> 
                  <hi>ſemen in terra pullulet, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcat, &amp; coligat fructum: Niſi cum doctrina experimentali prius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traverit in noſtram Philoſophiam Naturalem, &amp; non Sophiſticam, ſermocinalem illam, quae naſcitur Logicis, per diverſas praeſumptiones Phantaſticas: qui cum prognoſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus ſequelarum, contra vim Naturae, faciunt multos pertinaciter errare, in Sophiſticatione mentis. Quia per noſtram Mechanicam Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiam, intellectus eſt rectificatus, vi experientiae, reſpectu Oculi, &amp; verae notitiae mentalis. Imo experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae noſtrae, ſtant ſupra probationes Phantaſticas Concluſionum; ideo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que nec eas tolerant: Sed omnes alias Scientias oſtendunt Vivaciter intrare in intellectum. Unde dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps</hi>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:42743:86"/> 
                  <hi>intelligimus per Naturam, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus illud, quod eſt, &amp; quale eſt. Quia per talem Scientiam, Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus ſtut denudatus Superfluitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; erroribus, qui ipſum ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riò removent à veritate, propter praeſumptiones &amp; praejudicata, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita in concluſionibus. Hinc enim noſtri ſe direxerunt ad intrandum per quamlibet ſcientiam, (in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem experientiam) per artem, juxta Naturae curſum, in ſuis uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocis principiis. Spagyria enim ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, eſt ſpeculum veri intellectus: Monſtratque tangere, &amp; videre ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritates, earum, in claro lumine. Nec fert argumenta logicalia; quia nimis remota, &amp; longuinca, de claro lumine. Ideoque habet tabula ſmaragdina: Per hoc genus</hi>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:42743:86"/> 
                  <hi>demonſtrandi, fugiet à te omnis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritas, &amp; acquiritur tibi omnis fortitudinis, fortitudo fortis, vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens omnia ſubtilia, &amp; ſolida pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trans, propterea vocor Hermes Triſmegiſtus, habens tres, (id eſt omnes) Partes Philoſophiae, atque totius mundi Teleſmon; Haec ille in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter orare ergo, &amp; pulſare, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur Medium in Naturalibus, quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendi per ignem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="authors_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>I Deſign (God Willing) in a ſhort time to Publiſh a Compleat Hiſtory of Human Blood, both in its Natural and Morbid State.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:42743:87"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Daniel Brown,</hi> at the <hi>Black-Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>NOV<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M Lumen Chirurgicum:</hi> Or, A New Light of Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery. Wherein is Diſcovered a much more Safe and Speedy way of Curing Wounds, than hath hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore been uſually Practiſed. Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated with ſeveral Experiments made this Year in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Novum Lumen Chirurgicum Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatum:</hi> Or, The New Light of Chyrurgery Vindicated from the many unjuſt Aſperſions of ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Calumniators. With the Addition of ſome few Experiments made this Winter in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>Both by Jo. Colbatch, Phyſician.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42743:87"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
